Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 2 -- Letters to Franklin 1777 January-1778 March Mss.B.F85inventory02
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 May 23; A.L.S. 4p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Acknowledging the extract, which shall be published; will also print an article on the kindness of the Americans to their Hessian prisoners as contrasted with the behavior of the Royalists. Advisability of receiving the Journal of Congress regularly. Suggestions for an American currency. Begging him to visit them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 May 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Montaut, -----. Ile de Noirmoutier.
    Offers his services as surgeon; if he can be useful, is ready to leave at once for Bordeaux or whatever port Franklin may indicate; will accompany M. Tardeville who leaves for Paris to join Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 May 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Bicker, Lambertus. Rotterdam
    The bearer, his brother-in-law, Mr.Caarten, is going to France and Italy; he desires to pay his respects to Franklin and to present him with the first two volumes of their "Collections Académiques.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 May 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Baussay, Elias de, Dutch agent of Elector of Trier. La Haye
    A native of Amstordam; has been thirty-four years in the service of La Cour de Trèves, and has a perfect knowledge of the government of Holland; aware of everything which has passed between Franklin and the Ambassador of Holland. A visit from Franklin or Mr. Deane would be greeted with enthusiasm but does not think it would result in any real advantages, the Ambassador of England's influence being too strong. Suggests the advisability of Franklin having a secret agent in Holland; offers his services.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 May 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Alexander, William. Dijon
    Not surprised that M.Dubourg thought his terms too high; doubts not that he will get many cheaper undertakers. Sees his old friend Lee has been made Minister at Madrid; thinks he has much the air and manners of a Spaniard, when he is not angry; does Franklin know of his friend, the Counte de Rostaing, an officer of artillery? He claims to know a method of destroying ships in any river or roadstead, where there is no tide not current.
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1777 May 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Le Doigt, -----. Louviers.
    Hears that America is in need of carpenters, especially for the construction of mills; offers his services.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 May 24; A.L.S. 3p.; Arrenberg, Reinier. Rotterdam
    As he prints a Dutch newspaper, has copies and sent to the "Gazeteer Français de Leide" an account of the cruel treatment of the Americans by the English; begs to be informed of any important news from America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 May 24; A.L.S. 1p.; De Bragelonne de filley, de la Barre. Bordeaux
    Offering a new invention for use in war.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777 April 21]; Mem. 3p.; De Bragelonne de filley, de la Barre. Bordeaux
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 May 25; A.L. in 3d P.; Barbeu-Dubourg, -----
    Begs an audience for Mr. Coder, who has several models of costumes, ets., which merit special attention.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 May 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Sarsfield, Guy-Claude, comte de
    As he has received no answer from Franklin to his last note, is still in suspense about the books he may wish to have; Mr. Oudin will send them to Mr. Deane's upon receiving any note from Franklin written in French.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 May 26; L.S. 2p.; Jones, Nobel Wimberly. Savannah
    Many difficulties experienced by the State of Georgia, owing to their situation and their being destiture of shipping and seamen; have been unable to procure certain articles essentially requisite for their defense; writes by order of the Honorable House of General Assembly, who have deputed Captain de la Plaigne as their agent, to proceed to France and to procure such articles as are specified in their instructions to him. Important services rendered by Captain de la Plaigne to the American cause; recommends him to Franklin's particular notice.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777.] May 26; A.L. in 3d P. 1 p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Wishing to borrow a letter from M. Burck [Burke?] to the Sheriff of Bristol, urging the necessity of making peace with the American Colonies.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 May 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Coder, Henry
    Sends him the rest of the models, which M. Dubourg had intended to bring the day before; grievous state of Madame Dubourg's health; will call upon him to ascevtain his decision.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 May 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Strahan, William. London
    News of Franklin's friends in London; Small's opinion that his stay in Paris is to pave the way to a reconciliation; his great desire for peace on reasonable terms.
    Printed in Hale's Franklin in France.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 May 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, -----
    Can do nothing at present for Franklin but pray; his wife feebler than the day before and it is impossible for him to leave her; recommends a conference between Franklin, Deane and Bayard; belives that the affair can be turned to the satisfaction of all.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 May 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Shanly, James. Paris
    Left Ireland about six weeks before to wait on Franklin and offer his services to the American cause; many staunch friends of that cause in Ireland, but they dare not declare themselves openly; would have brought large packets for Franklin from home had it not been dangerous to carry them. Understands that officers are needed; his own experience in disciplining troops; should Franklin give him an encouraging answer, there are many people waiting only for that to follow him.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 May 30; A.L.S. Benj[amin] Harrison et al. 3p.; The Continental Congress, Committee of Foreign Affairs. Philadelphia
    Loan to be raised in France. France, Spain, and America, together, could expel the British fleet from the western seas.
    (In duplicate.)
    Printed in Diplom. Corres, Wharton, II, 327.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 May 31; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Hindrances in the way of loading the Mère Bobie. Report that Hammond is taken.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1777 may]; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Shanly, James
    Called on Dr. Franklin at Passy this Thursday morning; will call again to-morrow.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Coder, Henry
    Advised by M. Dubourg to send him the blue coat exactly like the model he showed him. Describes the rest of the uniform.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Richoufftz, Jean-Laurent-César, chevalier de. Douay
    Without occupation or fortune; begs Franklin to take pity on him and agree to his proposition to cross to Boston with the rank of captain and a salary of 2,400 livres in addition to the cost of his voyage.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Bruslé, -----. Paris
    Writes on behalf of a young man of good family, aged twenty-one, who desires to follow the profession of arms; heard that Franklin has procured for many soldiers the means of passing to America; begs that he may receive a like favor.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 1; A.L.S. 3p.; Burette, -----. Madrid
    The success of the Americans proves the justice of their cause; his desire to enter their army with the same rank he held in France; asks what are the necessary steps to be taken.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 1; A. L. S. 3p.; Burdett, P. P. Carlsruhe
    The bearer is Baron Steuben, a gentleman of family, merit, and great experience, well known to some of the first personages in Europe; he comes all the way from Germany to make the acquaintance of Dr. Franklin. Apologizes for having troubled him of late with so many letters, but his communication of too great importance to trust to the common post.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 1; A.L.S. 3p.; Sudrie, Gabriel-Joseph Cosson de la.
    Desires to enter the American army; his rank as captain.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 3; L.S. 3p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. Portsmouth, New Hampshire
    Has received orders from the Secret Committee of Congress to proceed in the French ship Amphitrite to Charlestown, S. C., and thence to Paris, put a letter in Franklin's hands, and take command of a "fine frigate"; refusal of the commander of the Amphitrite, M. Fautrel, to permit him to accompany him in any other capacity than as a passenger; Col. Langdon's proposal that he should proceed to France in a new Continental ship of war which he is now fitting out; probability of this proposition being adopted. Ardently desires to be again in active service; though personally unknown to Franklin, the prospect of being shortly under his direction affords him a singular pleasure.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Coder, Henry
    Arranging for an interview.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 3; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Ruault, -----. Paris
    Sends six copies of Franklin's words translated.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 3; A.L.S. in 3d P. 2p.; de Lauron, -----. Paris
    Requests to be made a Colonel of infantry, in the American army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 3; A.L.S. 4p.; de Lauron, -----. Paris
    In every effort to enter the American service he has failed. As a last resource he calls on Franklin but could not see him, so is now compelled to send him this letter requesting to be made a Colonel in the American army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Reculès de Basmarein & Raimbaux. Paris
    The bearer is M. Vanhammé possesses many secrets which might prove useful to America among them an easy and inexpensive manner of making salt-peter; wants to obtain a passage gratis and to carry certain letters of recommendation. Arrangements being made by them for two vessels to sail once a month for America; will take anyone Franklin recommends without any expense, if he so wishes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Smith, Josiah. London
    Born in Massachusetts, educated at Cambridge and studied physic and surgery until January, 1777, when he took ship for Bordeaux; gives an account of their capture by the English and their confinement in Plymouth; after two months obtained his freedom; treatment of the ship's company who, though they swore they were subjects of the United States, were forced into the service of the King. Two hundred Americans prisoners at Plymouth and as many more at Portsmouth; is coming to France to report their miserable condition to Franklin; his destitute state; begs Franklin to procure him a place as surgeon on some vessel; a friend of his, Capt. Brown, lately commander of a privateer, has just escaped and also would be glad of assistance.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 June 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Hillegas, Michael. Baltimore
    Supposes they are already acquainted with Congress having established a Continental Loan Office, taking money on interest; they will see by the late papers that far from being crushed, affairs look better than could have been expected.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 June 5; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Books on Cavalry to go by the Massachusetts; Count Pulaski and his two companions to embark on this ship; money advanced for their passage. Terms on which he can procure suits of clothing, shoes, saddles and holsters.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Porter, John. St. Malo
    Account of his capture, imprisonment at Plymouth and escape; is in a strange country and destitute of every necessary of life; desperate circumstances of his poor countrymen who are treated like felons in the prisons of Plymouth; English worse than the Turks; promised to tell Franklin of Capt. John Adams's capture.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 6; A.L.S. 4p.; Lownes, Caleb. son of John Lownes. London
    Giving an account of his time since he left Philadelphia till his arrival in London; the cause of his leaving America and his reasons for tarrying in England; wishes to know whether by staying he will hazard either his father's or his own reputation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 7; A.L.S. 4p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Concerning his proposed partnership with Mr. Schweighauser; strongly attached to this gentleman's family; stands extremely well with the second daughter; believes his present lack of means the only bar to a union. Account of his connection with a poor girl in England by whom he had a son; intends providing for the boy and later taking him altogether.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 7; A.L.S. 4p.; Massequan, -----. Nice
    Read in the London Evening Post that Franklin had already accorded letters of marque to thirty vessels of France in charge of American captains; a proposal he made to one Francis Fowler, a Scotchman, to take command of a vessel belonging to him, and to cruise against the "Tamisiens" [English?] in the Mediterranen. Requests Franklin to give a commission to this new patriot, whose honesty, courage and knowledge of the sea he can guarantee.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Sowden, Benjamin. Rotterdam
    Extracts from Mr. Gordon's letter to Dr. Price, published by Mr. Arrenberg in his Courant; subsequently copied in most of the other Courants of Holland. Concerning a French piece entitled "Avis aux Hessois" which has had a great vogue. Sir Joseph Yorke's bullying memorial to the States has given great offence in Holland; generally believed to have been composed by the King himself.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 7; A.L.S. 3p.; Fowler, Francis. Nice
    Is a subject of Great Britain, born in Aberdeen, and has served in different ships of his Majesty; describes the ship he has under his command, and asks Franklin for a commission, so that, unlooked for, he may cruise in the Mediterranean and fall upon the avowed enemies of the Royal Congress of America.1.
    1 See VI, 52.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 8; L.S. and Mem. 4p.; de Cardone, -----. Paris
    Sending a memoir, intended for Congress, on the advantages to America of having large flour mills and builidng up an extensive export trade in that and similar articles.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Deane, Silas. Paris
    Expects M. Coder, who has proposed to furnish the clothes the following morning; asks Franklin to breakfast with him then. The letter to Mr. Jay is a summary of what they last wrote, but written in secret ink and to all appearance about unimportant matters.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent. Paris
    They are going to repeat several of Dr. Priestley's principal experiments on different kinds of air; if these will interest Franklin, will be honored with his presence.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Mease, Matthew. Paris
    Writes on behalf of some gentlemen who are desirous of Franklin's advice, to ask if he will grant them an interview.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 June 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Capture of Adams verified by Captain Porter who has just arrived; assistance given this captain; his intention to go out on some armed vessel and revenge his losses; thinks Wickes or Johnson would find him a valuable acquisition.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 June 10; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Asking their interest on behalf of a poor American sailor who has been falsely accused of murder; gives the affair in detail.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, -----
    If he likes the model that M. Coder showed him, advises him to decide on it at once, as in a few days prices will go up. Concerning the muskets which he spoke to him about before.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 11; A.L.S. 3p.; Cavalier, -----. Lyons
    His admiration for the Americans; wishes to fly to their defense.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 11; A.L.S. 1p.; de Thuillières, Baron. Paris
    Requests Franklin to appoint a time when he can receive Mme. Denneville and Vicomtesse de Choiseul, from Martinique, who wish to see him. Asks about a balsam remedy offered to him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 12; A.L.S. 1p.; De Brétigney, -----. Paris
    Asking for a letter of introduction of Franklin's nephew [Jonathan Williams, Jr.], for three officers, leaving for America, via Nantes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 12; A.L.S. 4p.; Timothy, Peter
    Congratulates him on the honors conferred by " The Thirteen United Free and Independent States." His many positions on committees and congresses and his active interest in public affairs left him no time for private correspondence. Wishes some instruction on a plan of education for his son, Benjamin Franklin, aged six.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Coder, Henry
    Concerning the models in cloth; wil not rest until he is en route for America; hopes to merit the praise of Congress and the confidence and esteem of the generals and the friendship of the Americans.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Lee, William. Paris
    Informing Franklin that Mr. Deane and himself will do themselves the honor of breakfasting with him on Sunday at 9 o'clock.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 13; A.L.S. 8p.; d'Ordan, Cot. Lille
    Wishes to devote himself to the cause of America; has been employed in the Commissary Department and would like a similar position. if possible, in America; ready to serve such a cause with either pen or sword; if he receives a favorable reply will set out at once for Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Caffiéri, Jean Jacques
    Wishes to know various details concerning Gen. Montgomery, the dates of his birth and death, his most famous actions and how and where he was killed in the attack on Quebec. Intends making a model of the monument for the next salon, and wishes to give a description of the tomb and of the person for whom it was made. (In French.)
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 June 13; A.L.S. Benj[amin] Harrison et al. 2p.; The Continental Congress, Committee of Foreign Affairs. Philadelphia
    General Washington's successes in New Jersey. Everything still quiet in the Northern Department. Favorable aspect of affairs.
    Printed in Diplom. Corres., Wharton, II, 336.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 June 14; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan.
    Arrival of the Anonyme; poor opinion of her ability either to fight or run away; officers claiming passage on her; question of her destination. Reported blowing up of Mr. Chaumont's ship Captain Rotch at the entrance of the Delaware. Ships at present for sale.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Thiérin, Ph F. Paris
    Had the honor to give Franklin a letter from one of his friends of St. Malo; reminds Franklin of his promise to answer it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 Jube 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Girard, chevalier de. Paris.
    Desires an interview with Franklin; has received a letter from Cherbourg with information of the capture of an English vessel.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Courreget, ------, fils. Bayonne
    Writes on behalf of a young Frenchman, aged twenty-five years, who wishes to enter that glorious company and perish, if need be, with Franklin's brave compatriots.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 16; A.L.S 1p.; Coder, Henry
    M. Dalibard secks an interview concerning the muskets; expects to be at Passy himself at 8 o'clock the next morning. Madame Dubourg's dangerous condition. Copy of four lines, written by M. Dubourg at the foot of Franklin's picture.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Laville, D
    A letter of recommendation for one Bumel.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 17; The Royal Society of Medicine of Paris. Paris
    Certificate of membership.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Basserode, Jean-Baptiste-Guillaume Leprévôt, chevalier de. Tonnay-Charente
    Fears that his letter of April never reached Franklin; sends copy of it.
    (See V, 158.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Introducing Mr. Frerot, a cannon-founder of Nantes, who hopes to obtain permission of the Ministry to make what quantity of cannon he pleases; advantages of obtaining them at the place of shipping.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 18; A.L.S. 1p.; De Brétigney, -----. Paris
    Asking permission to call to present his officers, to say good-by, and to get letters of introduction for himself and officers to Congress.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 June 18; A.L.S. Benj[amin] Harrison et al. 4p.; The Continental Congress, Committee of Foreign Affairs. Philadelphia
    Skirmishes in the Northern Department. Military affairs in New Jersey.
    (In Duplicate.)
    Printed in Diplom. Corres, Wharton, II, 344.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Douglas, Archibald. Cherbourg
    Is now lying in Cherbourg with the same prize that Capt. John Burnell informed Franklin of; does not know what to do with her owing to the loss of their captain and the impossibility of selling her; two King's cutters cruising off the harbor on purpose to take them should they venture out; wishes to know how he shall act.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Haines, R. Paris
    Assured by his sister (Sarah Evans) that Franklin will not be offended at his writing to him. Concerning the sale of some land in the northern part of the province of New York belonging to a Mr.Lydius, who thought Franklin might know of a purchaser.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Paradise, N?. Homburg Vor-der-Höhe
    Is Secretary of the Patriotic Society of Homburg; desires to add Franklin's name and those of some of his brave and learned compatriots to the membership. Concerning the memoirs that the society proposes to publish. In Germany there are certain writers in the employ of Lord North to abuse the Americans, French and Spanish.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 June 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Can obtain an old French frigate, which could be fitted for a privateer, and enough Americans to man her, in case they care to encourage an operation of a warlike nature.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Bridgen, Edward. Antwerp
    Sends him a letter from Dr. Price; gives his address in case Franklin wishes to send back an answer. Places the Bishop's Sermon, printed in the enclosed newspaper, at Franklin's service.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Coder, Henry
    Concerning the models he sent to Mr. Deane which have been appropriated by the "regisseurs"; begs him to write a line to Mr.Deane in order that he may recover his models.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 20; A.L.S. 1p.; d'Antrecourt, Abbé. Paris
    His brother desires to enter the American Army; his brother's knowledge of mathematics and war.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Brétigney, Charles-François Sevelinges, marquis(?) de.
    Sends him a letter from M. de Beaumarchais; begs him to give the bearer the letters he promised.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Krohne, G. B. de. Hamburg
    Is minister plenipotentiary of the Duke of Saxe-Hildburghausen; has the requisite talent to serve America, being equipped with a full knowledge of business and politics; admirable position of Hamburg as a center of news and commerce; all he asks as a reward besides the payment of his expenses, is a promise from the Congress to declare him their minister as soon as the Colonies obtain their independence.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.